[
  {
    "chunk_number": 1,
    "text_preview": "Page 1 of 51 Biology is a word derived from two Greek words i.e. ‚ÄúBios‚Äù and ‚Äúlogos‚Äù where Bios means life and logos means knowledge. Therefore Biology is the study of life or living things. All living...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of living things?",
        "answer": "Therefore Biology is the study of life or living things.",
        "term": "living things"
      },
      {
        "question": "Describe Nutrition.",
        "answer": "Nutrition, the study of food and how living things feed.",
        "term": "Nutrition"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 2,
    "text_preview": "Page 3 of 51 Determination of magnification using a hand lens Magnification refers to how much larger the object appears compared to its real size. Magnification = ùë†ùëñùëßùëí ùëúùëì ùë°‚Ñéùëí ùëñùëöùëéùëîùëí/ùëëùëüùëéùë§ùëñùëõùëî ùë†ùëñùëßùëí ùëúùëì ùë°‚Ñé...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Eye Piece.",
        "answer": "Eye Piece: It is where the eye is placed while viewing the specimen Enables one to view the specimen It magnifies the image from the objective lens.",
        "term": "Eye Piece"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 3,
    "text_preview": "Page 4 of 51 6. Stand / Base: Supports instrument in on a flat surface. 7. Diaphragm: Regulates the amount of light passing through the specimen. 8. Condenser: Concentrates the light reflected by the ...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of objective lens?",
        "answer": "Objective lens: Magnifies the specimen under study.",
        "term": "objective lens"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 4,
    "text_preview": "Page 5 of 51 Cell parts and their functions Cell part Description Function 1. Cell Membrane Is the outer living part of a cell and it is found in all cells. Its semi permeable i.e. has tiny holes thro...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define the cell.",
        "answer": "It allows movement of materials in and out of the cell.",
        "term": "the cell"
      },
      {
        "question": "Describe Store.",
        "answer": "Controls cell division Stores the genetic material of a cell Plays an active role in protein synthesis.",
        "term": "Store"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 6,
    "text_preview": "Page 7 of 51 LEVELS OF ORGANISATION Cell ‚ü∂ tissue ‚ü∂ organ ‚ü∂ organ system‚ü∂organism Level of organization Definition Examples and functions 1. Cell Smallest basic unit of life Red blood cell, root hair ...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of organ system?",
        "answer": "Page 7 of 51 LEVELS OF ORGANISATION Cell ‚ü∂ tissue ‚ü∂ organ ‚ü∂ organ system‚ü∂organism Level of organization Definition Examples and functions 1.",
        "term": "organ system"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 7,
    "text_preview": "Page 8 of 51 CLASSIFICATION OF LIVING ORGANISMS Classification is the process of placing animals and plants into groups according to their similarities in structure, physiological processes and behavi...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Class.",
        "answer": "Page 8 of 51 CLASSIFICATION OF LIVING ORGANISMS Classification is the process of placing animals and plants into groups according to their similarities in structure, physiological processes and behavioral.",
        "term": "Class"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of Species?",
        "answer": "The largest taxon is the kingdom and the smallest taxon is the species.",
        "term": "Species"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 9,
    "text_preview": "Page 10 of 51 iv) Used in curing tea and tobacco, making silage /retting flax. Curing is process of treating and preserving tea / tobacco v) Bacteria destroys harmful organisms in sewage in the sewage...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Amoeba?",
        "answer": "Examples of protozoa include Amoeba, Paramecium, Euglena, Trypanosome and plasmodium.",
        "term": "Amoeba"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 12,
    "text_preview": "Page 13 of 51 KINGDOM PLANTAE This kingdom contains multicellular organisms whose cells contain chlorophyll and are covered by a cellulose cell wall. General characteristics They are mostly green in c...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Ferns.",
        "answer": "Pteridophyta: This is made up of ferns.",
        "term": "Ferns"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of DIVISION?",
        "answer": "The kingdom is divided into two main divisions i.e.",
        "term": "DIVISION"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 15,
    "text_preview": "Page 16 of 51 Askaris lumbricoides 5. Phylum: Annelida (ringed worm) These are the ringed or segmented worms e.g. earthworms, leeches, rag worms, lugworms, etc. The earthworm The body wall has three b...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Phylum?",
        "answer": "Phylum: Annelida (ringed worm) These are the ringed or segmented worms e.g.",
        "term": "Phylum"
      },
      {
        "question": "Define Class.",
        "answer": "Phylum Arthropoda comprises of classes Crustacea, Chilopoda, Diplopoda, Insecta and Arachnida.",
        "term": "Class"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of Crustacea?",
        "answer": "Phylum Arthropoda comprises of classes Crustacea, Chilopoda, Diplopoda, Insecta and Arachnida.",
        "term": "Crustacea"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 16,
    "text_preview": "Page 17 of 51 They have a pair of antenna They have one pair of mouthparts known as mandibles. They have one pair of legs on each body segment. They are carnivorous. 3. Class: Diplopoda Class Diplopod...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Millipedes.",
        "answer": "Class: Diplopoda Class Diplopoda is made up of millipedes.",
        "term": "Millipedes"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 19,
    "text_preview": "Page 20 of 51 EXTERNAL FEATURES, LIFE CYCLES AND ECONOMIC IMPORTANCE OF SELECTED INSECTS A branch of biology that deals with the study of insects is known as entomology. Insects exhibit the longest le...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Insect.",
        "answer": "Page 20 of 51 EXTERNAL FEATURES, LIFE CYCLES AND ECONOMIC IMPORTANCE OF SELECTED INSECTS A branch of biology that deals with the study of insects is known as entomology.",
        "term": "Insect"
      },
      {
        "question": "Describe COCKROACH.",
        "answer": "Insects showing this include locusts, grasshoppers, bedbugs, cockroaches, and termites.",
        "term": "COCKROACH"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 20,
    "text_preview": "Page 21 of 51 NB: Other insects belonging to the order Dictyoptera include; weevils, beetles, ladybirds. Habitat: Cockroaches live in dark, dirty and dump warm places e.g. pipes that carry sewage. Dur...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Describe Habitat.",
        "answer": "Habitat: Cockroaches live in dark, dirty and dump warm places e.g.",
        "term": "Habitat"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 23,
    "text_preview": "Page 24 of 51 The thorax: The thorax consists of prothorax, mesothorax and metathorax. These segments are covered by hairs and divisions are not clearly seen. Each thoracic segment bears a pair of joi...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Describe Body.",
        "answer": "When the butterfly is flying, the wings are spread out but when at rest, the wings are raised and held vertically above the body.",
        "term": "Body"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 24,
    "text_preview": "Page 25 of 51 THE HOUSE FLY (Musca domestica) Classification Taxon Reason Kingdom Animalia Cells lack chlorophyll i.e. cannot make their own food. Phylum Arthropoda It has a hard exoskeleton. It has s...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Explain Musca.",
        "answer": "Page 25 of 51 THE HOUSE FLY (Musca domestica) Classification Taxon Reason Kingdom Animalia Cells lack chlorophyll i.e.",
        "term": "Musca"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 26,
    "text_preview": "Page 27 of 51 The mosquitoes are majorly found in the tropics and are best known for carrying disease germs They belong to the order Diptera and the important three genera are: i) Anopheles that are v...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Plasmodium?",
        "answer": "The disease causing parasite is referred to as plasmodium.",
        "term": "Plasmodium"
      },
      {
        "question": "Define Malaria.",
        "answer": "Page 27 of 51 The mosquitoes are majorly found in the tropics and are best known for carrying disease germs They belong to the order Diptera and the important three genera are: i) Anopheles that are vectors of malaria.",
        "term": "Malaria"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 27,
    "text_preview": "Page 28 of 51 Control of spread of malaria Of these diseases malaria is probably becoming the most serious and is increasingly becoming a killer of such great as AIDS. This is mainly because the paras...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Larva.",
        "answer": "Appropriate measures include; Destroying the breeding places where larvae develop from by draining or applying a film of oil over the water surface to prevent oxygen reaching the mosquito larva.",
        "term": "Larva"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 31,
    "text_preview": "Page 32 of 51 FLOWERING PLANTS These are plants that bear flowers. A typical flowering plant is composed of 2 systems i.e: Root system and Shoot system The two systems are made up of two categories of...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of ROOTS?",
        "answer": "They include roots, stems and leaves.",
        "term": "ROOTS"
      },
      {
        "question": "Explain flowering plant.",
        "answer": "Page 32 of 51 FLOWERING PLANTS These are plants that bear flowers.",
        "term": "flowering plant"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 33,
    "text_preview": "Page 34 of 51 7. Epiphytic roots These grow on certain plants called epiphytes. Epiphytes are plants which grow and get support from other plants. These roots hang freely in the atmosphere. They absor...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Root.",
        "answer": "Epiphytic roots These grow on certain plants called epiphytes.",
        "term": "Root"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of ROOT?",
        "answer": "Epiphytic roots These grow on certain plants called epiphytes.",
        "term": "ROOT"
      },
      {
        "question": "Describe Epiphytes.",
        "answer": "Epiphytic roots These grow on certain plants called epiphytes.",
        "term": "Epiphytes"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 35,
    "text_preview": "Page 36 of 51 3) Underground stems These are modified stems which remain permanently underground. They are often swollen and serve as food storage organs. NB: Annual herbs only live for one year Bi ‚Äì ...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Describe Tendrils.",
        "answer": "Climbing stems These are stems that grow clinging to the support of other plants by means of tendrils.",
        "term": "Tendrils"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 36,
    "text_preview": "Page 37 of 51 Underground stems There are four types of underground stems namely: Rhizome, Corm, Stem tuber and Bulb. 1. Rhizomes This is a horizontal thick underground stem having adventitious roots ...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Bulb.",
        "answer": "Page 37 of 51 Underground stems There are four types of underground stems namely: Rhizome, Corm, Stem tuber and Bulb.",
        "term": "Bulb"
      },
      {
        "question": "Explain Rhizome.",
        "answer": "Page 37 of 51 Underground stems There are four types of underground stems namely: Rhizome, Corm, Stem tuber and Bulb.",
        "term": "Rhizome"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 37,
    "text_preview": "Page 38 of 51 5. Corm A corm is a swollen fleshy underground stem that grows in a vertical direction. It is round-shaped and somehow flattened from the top to bottom. It has a terminal bud lying at th...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Phloem?",
        "answer": "They consist of xylem and phloem.",
        "term": "Phloem"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 42,
    "text_preview": "Page 43 of 51 INTERNAL STRUCTURE OF A LEAF 1. Epidermis: This is the outer most layer of a leaf. It‚Äôs covered by a transparent water porous layer of cutin called cuticle. This cuticle allows light pen...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Epidermis?",
        "answer": "Epidermis: This is the outer most layer of a leaf.",
        "term": "Epidermis"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 43,
    "text_preview": "Page 44 of 51 The palisade cells contain many chloroplasts which are the major sites for photosynthesis. Chloroplasts are small and made up of proteins. They contain chlorophyll which gives green plan...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Describe Calyx.",
        "answer": "The four floral whorls are Calyx, Corolla, Gynoecium and Androecium.",
        "term": "Calyx"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 44,
    "text_preview": "Page 45 of 51 Types of ovaries The two types of ovaries include the following 1. Superior ovary: Is the one that arises above the other floral parts e.g. hibiscus, cassia, mimosa pudica, etc. 2. Infer...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Describe Hypogenous.",
        "answer": "Hypogenous: The gynoecium is situated at the apex of the receptacle and other whorls arise below it.",
        "term": "Hypogenous"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 45,
    "text_preview": "Page 46 of 51 They have sticky stigmas, which hold pollen grains. They produce few sticky pollen grains. They produce heavy pollen grains. They produce nectar from nectarines to attract insects. Chara...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Insect.",
        "answer": "They produce nectar from nectarines to attract insects.",
        "term": "Insect"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of Flowers?",
        "answer": "Characteristics of wind pollinated flowers.",
        "term": "Flowers"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 46,
    "text_preview": "Page 47 of 51 Types of seeds Monocotyledonous seeds: These contain only one seed leaf or cotyledon. E.g. cereals like maize. Dicotyledonous seeds: These contain 2 cotyledons e.g. legumes like beans, p...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Define Cotyledon.",
        "answer": "Page 47 of 51 Types of seeds Monocotyledonous seeds: These contain only one seed leaf or cotyledon.",
        "term": "Cotyledon"
      },
      {
        "question": "Explain Radicle.",
        "answer": "iv) Radicle: It is a seed root (embryo root) which develops into primary root of the plant.",
        "term": "Radicle"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 47,
    "text_preview": "Page 48 of 51 Classification of fruits There are 3 groups of fruits namely; i) Simple fruits These are formed from one flower in which the pistil consists of either one carpel (monocarpic) or of sever...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is the purpose of Achene?",
        "answer": "These are Achene, Nut, Caryopsis, Cypsela and Samara.",
        "term": "Achene"
      },
      {
        "question": "Explain Type.",
        "answer": "Types of simple fruits Simple fruits are further divided into three categories.",
        "term": "Type"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 48,
    "text_preview": "Section through a cashew nut Caryopsis. This is an achene-like fruit in which the testa and pericarp are fused. These are mainly found in grasses and maize. Caryopsis of maize Cypsela This is a fruit ...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Caryopsis?",
        "answer": "Section through a cashew nut Caryopsis.",
        "term": "Caryopsis"
      },
      {
        "question": "Define Samara.",
        "answer": "tridax and bidens pilosa Cypsela of tridax Samara.",
        "term": "Samara"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 49,
    "text_preview": "Page 49 of 51 Dry dehiscent fruits These are fruits with a dry pericarp that splits (dehisces) to release seeds. The fruits split at particular lines of weakness known as sutures. These fruits are cat...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Legume?",
        "answer": "These fruits include, Follicles, Legume, Capsule and Schizocarp.",
        "term": "Legume"
      },
      {
        "question": "Define Schizocarp.",
        "answer": "These fruits include, Follicles, Legume, Capsule and Schizocarp.",
        "term": "Schizocarp"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 50,
    "text_preview": "Page 50 of 51 Tranverse section through a berry (tomato) 3. Pome This is a succulent fruit in which the outer fleshy (normally edible) part develops from the calyx and receptacle. The ovary forms a pa...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Explain Type.",
        "answer": "There are five types of placentation as shown in the table below.",
        "term": "Type"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "chunk_number": 52,
    "text_preview": "Page 52 of 51 Self-dispersal a) explosive mechanism This happens with dry dehiscent fruits. The pericarp splits open along the sutures to release the seeds. This is made possible due to the tension th...",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "What is Self?",
        "answer": "Page 52 of 51 Self-dispersal a) explosive mechanism This happens with dry dehiscent fruits.",
        "term": "Self"
      }
    ]
  }
]